<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The iaylors conuersion Wherein is liuely represented, the true image of a soule rightlye touched, and conuerted by the spirit of God. The waightie circumstances of which supernaturall worke, for the sweete amplifications, and fit applications to the present time, are now set downe for the comfort of the strong, and confirmation of the weake. By Hugh Dowriche Batch. of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Dowriche, Hugh, b. 1552 or 3.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111947</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847206</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847206</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12230</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20782)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 218:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The iaylors conuersion Wherein is liuely represented, the true image of a soule rightlye touched, and conuerted by the spirit of God. The waightie circumstances of which supernaturall worke, for the sweete amplifications, and fit applications to the present time, are now set downe for the comfort of the strong, and confirmation of the weake. By Hugh Dowriche Batch. of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Dowriche, Hugh, b. 1552 or 3.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 26 [i.e. 28] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Windet, dwelling at Pauls wharfe, at the signe of the crosse keyes, and are there to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1]596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Last leaf misnumbered.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Protestant authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12230:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12230:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>THE IAYLORS Conuerſion.</p>
            <p>Wherein is liuely repreſented, the true Image of a Soule rightlye touched, and conuerted by the ſpirit of God.</p>
            <p>The waightie circumſtances of which ſupernaturall worke, for the ſweete ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, and fit applications to the preſent time, are now ſet downe for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the ſtrong, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the weake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Hugh Dowriche <hi>Batch. of Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>The Lord maketh poore, and maketh rich: bringeth low and exalteth.</hi> 
               <bibl>1. <hi>Samu.</hi> 2. 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Behold now, for I, I am he, and there is no gods with me: I kill, &amp; giue life: I wound, and make whole: neither is there any that can deliuer out of my hand,</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 32, 39</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Iohn Windet, dwelling at Pauls Wharfe, at the ſigne of the Croſſe Keyes, and are there to be ſolde. 1596.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12230:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12230:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull, and <hi>my approued good Friende:</hi> Valentine Knightly Eſquire, long proſperitie, and peace of conſcience in Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed is hee (ſayth Dauid) whoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe is forgiuen and whoſe ſinne is couered, &amp;c. Here is one Medicine for two maladies: here is one ſalue that heales two ſores. Sinne is the teſtie botch that may not be touched. All are infected with this plague: but heere is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, ſome ſee it not at al, ſome ſee it too much, ſome feele it, &amp; feare it, ſome nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feare it, nor feele it. In ſome negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent blindneſſe, and ſecuritie breeds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of imminent perill; in ſome, the
<pb facs="tcp:12230:3"/> view of great daunger accompanied with feare without faith, commits them to the dangerous downefall of a deadly deſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. The one ſeeth not his ſinne, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeketh no remedie; the other ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with ſinne, findeth not the meanes to applie the remedie. Heere is both the remedie and the application. Ther is a meane betwene theſe extremes: This meane is, to ſee our ſinne, our naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, our wickednes, but ſo, as we alwaies haue one eye on our ſelues and our ſin, the other, on Chriſt and his merits. If we ſee our ſins in themſelues, they exceede in number the ſands of the Sea, in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the compaſſe of the whole world. If we then goe about to match them, with our owne power, ſtrength, or merites, how infinitly ſhall we bee ouerwhelmed in this compariſon? But if we, leauing our ſelues, fly to the power of God, by which he can; and his mercie in Ieſus Chriſt, by which he will deliuer vs from this infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plague; we ſhall preſently ſee, both ſin, hell, and Sathan to conſume as ſmoke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the preſence of our God. Sin is the plague, ſinne is the ſore: The medicine is,
<pb facs="tcp:12230:3"/> the mercy of God, thorough Ieſus Chriſt in whome, and by whome, our ſinnes are forgiuen. This mercie is apprehended by faith, and faith is the gift of God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when we haue caſt vp all our recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, we ſhall find, that all our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and all our merites, (in reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, to merite ſaluation) are nothing elſe but the righteouſnes and merites of Chriſt, imputed to vs by the mercie of God, by which our ſinnes are pardoned. And therefore with Saint Paule euerie man, to his owne Conſcience, may right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, <hi>What haſt thou, which thou haſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued?</hi> Yet, to this mercie there is tyed a bleſſing, and a curſe, to ſhewe the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the reprobate, and the children of God. They, which by mercy, attaine this mercy, are truely called bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; They which for want of mercie, are depriued of this mercy, are iuſtly accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But can there bee in one, and one ſo certaine and immutable cauſe, ſuch, and ſuch diuers effects? Can mercy be found without mercy? Can light be ſeene with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out light? Can fire be felt without heate? What more contrarie the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:12230:4"/> then glorie, &amp; confuſion? Yet one, and the ſelfe ſame fire, makes golde more glorious, which vtterly conſumes wood, ſtraw, and ſtubble. What is more contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie then hard, and ſoft? yet one and the ſelfe ſame ſunne doth harden the dirte, and mollifieth the waxe. Theſe contrarie effects proceede not from any contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that is found in the pure and ſimple eſſence either of Sunne or fire, but from the diuerſitie which lyeth hid in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſubiects, on which they work. The mercy of God, being ſtill one and the ſame, is offered to al without reſpect, (as the Sunne ſhines and the raine fals, as well on the vniuſt as the iuſt) but all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it not. The wicked ſee it, but deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe it, and make a ieſt of it, till, by the iuſt iudgement of God they periſh in theyr wickedneſſe, as did Pharao, Iudas, and the wicked ſonnes of Elie, &amp;c. The elect, being moued by the ſpirit of God, do ſee, lament, and repent their ſinnes, and ſo by mercy obtaine pardon. So that, though, both the elect and the reprobate are both alike happie, in that mercy is offered to both a like, yet becauſe the wicked refuſe
<pb facs="tcp:12230:4"/> it, they are iuſtly accurſed; and the other that receiue, and take hold of it, are here accounted happie and bleſſed. And yet not bleſſed in reſpect of any work or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe in themſelues, but that, by the merits of Chriſt, (which they apprehend by faith) they are by mercy and imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, made worthy of this bleſsing. This then is the golden meane, that makes the godly bleſſed to beholde their ſinnes by faith in Chriſt; and not as the reprobate, either, not to ſee them at all, or, without faith to behold them. Of this meane, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid himſelfe tooke happie hold-faſt. For now, conducted by mercie, and faith, we ſee, how luſtely hee leapes out from the hote-houſe of deſperate temptations in which it ſeemes (at the making of this Pſalme) he was deepely plunged, by the terror of a guiltie conſcience, touched by the hand of God, for the ſinne which he had committed with Barſheba. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of his paſsions and the vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of his conflicts, are deſcribed in the 3. and 4. verſes of this Pſalme. Now this is not Dauids caſe alone; but it is certaine, that all the children of God, that are elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:12230:5"/> in his eternall purpoſe, in their times appointed, ſhal heare the like calling and taſt of the like mercy. For manifeſtation of the which, wee may ſee an example of the ſame mercy, which the Lord ſhewed vnto a ſimple and ſinfull man, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Iailor of Phillippy; of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the 16. of the Acts ther is an honorable memorie left to al poſterity. K. Dauid, &amp; this Iaylor, were both ſinners; both of them acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the hand of God heauie vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their ſinnes; the one, called to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by the voice of a man; the other, ſhaken from his drowſineſſe, by the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of an Earthquake; both felt comfort in their miſeries, by the mercy of GOD, which kept them from deſperation. The rarenes of which example, the great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God; and the ſingular inſtructions that riſe, to the profit of ſuch as deepely waigh the whole action; beſides the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire of ſome, whoſe requeſt I could not denie; haue drawne me now, to ſet downe certaine notes, and conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons touching the ſingular working of the ſpirit of God in this man, vttered long ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence vpon occaſion; which I haue ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb facs="tcp:12230:5"/> 
               <hi>The Iaylors Conuerſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being the firſt thing of mine, that euer paſt the preſſe; I thought to make bold, to Dedicate it, to the firſt friend, that euer was truely poſſeſſed of my hart. The firſt fruits were ſtil moſt accepted &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of the Lord; The firſt childe, by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is beſt beloued of the father: The firſt faith is euer moſt firme, moſt deare and ſweete to the poſſeſſor: My firſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full affection, hath inforced me, to offer theſe ſimple firſt fruites, to you that had the gift of my firſt faith. Which affection you firſt wonne by curteſie, &amp; after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it by deſert; which, being planted young, hath now growne to be olde: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing begun long ſithence, hath continued to this preſent, inuiolable; and as the greene bayes, (whome no tempeſt can blaſt) euer flouriſhing; &amp; (ſo I hope) ſhal continue ſo long, as life ſhal giue leaue to loue. If I could as eaſily beſtow on you, a great part of the world, as I doe willingly giue you this ſmal portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of words, thogh you bee great already, yet would I make you greater: But ſeing words for want of welth, muſt ſhewe my will, conſider in
<pb facs="tcp:12230:6"/> theſe words, not the words, but the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſpirit of God. And I dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſay, that if you can imitate right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this one example, theſe words in ſhort time, though you bee good already, yet ſhall they make you better.</p>
            <p>The Lord, that hath giuen you a great portion of faith, &amp; hath beſtowed on you great worldly bleſsings of wiſedome and welth, increaſe this faith, &amp; ſo dayly mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie theſe bleſsings vpon you, that you may go forward, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith to faith, from vertue to vertue, from life to life, till in the day of the Lord, your imperfections being made perfect, you may receiue the Crowne of immortall glorie, prepared for ſuch as loue the Lord vnfainedly. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niton in Deuon, this 30. daye of Iune. 1596.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing friend. Hugh Dowriche.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:12230:6"/>
               <l>Vaine floting blaſtes of worldly bliſſe, that neuer ſtay,</l>
               <l>Are ſmoke-like, mounting ſpied, but quickly quite decay.</l>
               <l>Like vewes of fawning ſhades, that plant alluring baytes,</l>
               <l>Erre fully come, their farwell ſhewes, their hid deceytes.</l>
               <l>No truſt, in truſtleſſe traſh, no faith in friendly ſhewes,</l>
               <l>Truth quailes in Hectik fits, whilſt falſhoode greenely growes.</l>
               <l>Yea, masking viſars fraude, great grace, in graceleſſe findes,</l>
               <l>No place, for naked truth, No time, for fraudleſſe mindes,</l>
               <l>Eſteemed vice ſoores high, on gales of witleſſe windes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Knocke</hi> VViſedome <hi>while ſhe faint, on rocke of flintie hart,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No anſwere, but, I will not come, you may depart,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If ſupreame voice, to</hi> Conſcience <hi>call, to counte for ſinne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Greene Figleaues, grace defects, as ſinne had neuer binne.</l>
               <l>Hygh Cedars ſtoutly vaunt, that fruitleſſe harueſt yeelde,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Volgo, <hi>bright, yet good, for neither fiſh nor feelde.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let not falſe Suſis ſprings, finde poores in Corkie hart,</l>
               <l>Yeelde not to looſe the truth, though clad in carefull ſmart,</l>
               <l>Eſtabliſh vertues throne, And ſay to ſinne, depart.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12230:7"/>
            <head>To the friendly Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is dayly preaching, and daily printing of good Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and good Bookes, and yet there is little profiting, and little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment ſeene to follow, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in words or workes. We haue had precept vpon precept, Sermon vpon Sermon; in euery corner, here a little, and there a little, and yet <hi>Egypt cannot ſpeake the language of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <note place="margin">Eſay. 8 13. Eſay. 19. 18.</note>
               </hi> Some profeſſors cannot ſee what is belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their profeſsion, &amp; liue there after.<hi>The Vineyeard yeeldeth but briers &amp; thornes.</hi> The companie of vaine, Papiſticall, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, <note place="margin">Eſay. 27. 5. Ierem. 7. 11</note> and Machiauelion profeſſors, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions to theeues, they are euen found to be the den and the ſinke of loth ſome hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; which the eye of Chriſt viewed, his heart lothed, his whip purged. The ſwords edge is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated to them, it cannot <hi>Pearce: the ſhaft is ſhot in vaine, it cannot ſticke.</hi> The force of
<pb facs="tcp:12230:7"/> the Goſpell, is become now ſo weake, it cannot moue them.<hi>The bellowes are burnt, the ledde is conſumed in the fire, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">Ierem. 6 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> hath melted in vaine.</hi> The preachers haue loſt their labours, and the Printers haue ſpent their care, their time, their ſtrength in nothing, for <hi>The wicked yet ſtill wreſtle againſt God, like wild Buls tumbling in a <note place="margin">Ierem. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> net:</hi> yea, they haue made a new couenant with death, and with hell: they haue clapped hands vpon a new bargaine. As Sathan told Eua ſhe ſhould not die ſo our lying fancies haue told vs, that,<hi>No plague ſhall come neere vs.</hi> Long peace and wealth hath brought vs to wanton <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> Babels eſtate: we are a virgine not to be oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by any; we are tender and delicate, the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe of felicitie; we are a Lady of kingdomes, with a pereleſſe proſperitie, in the middeſt of <note place="margin">Eſay. 47. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> our neighbours miſeries, wee neuer feared of our owne calamities, our necke is framed of yron ſinewes, it cannot bow; our browes are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-plated <note place="margin">Eſay: 48. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> with braſſe, they cannot bluſh. The trumpe hath blowen, yet can bee not bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine them that <hi>Were loſt in the land of Aſsiria:</hi> Though the preachers with their Cornets haue ſeuen and ſeuen times compaſſed Iericho, yet the curſed wals fal not; though the
<pb facs="tcp:12230:8"/> voice, the crie, and the force of the Goſpell, of ſignes and wonders haue beene heard and felt in euery corner, yet the weedes ouertoppe the Corne: the ſoule loſt in the ſincke of error and land of tranſgreſsion, returnes not againe: the Papiſts deceiued by the full fleſh pots of Egypt are not yet reclaimed; the Atheiſts, Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, Libertines, and carnall, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and diſſolute profeſſors, that are for their ſinne ſuffered to be led into hereſies, are not yet contented to ioyne in one godly vnitie to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſerue the Lord in the mount of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, the viſion of peace. We doe not yet ſee that bleſſed time, when Ephraim ſhall be are no euill will to Iuda; nor Iuda vexe Ephraim, when preachers ſhall not wrangle for trifels and bee deuided one from an other, but all ioyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to flie vpon the ſhoulders of the Pihliſtins the common enemies of the Goſpell. All our preaching cannot draw on that happie time, when, <hi>Iuda and Iſrael, ſhall walke both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> When all preachers and profeſſors that now hate, backbite, and ſlaunder one an other ſhall ſo ioyne hands and hearts together, that neither of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> walke or continue any longer in the hardneſſe of their froward harts. It was a certaine ſigne of Gods heauie plague againſt
<pb facs="tcp:12230:8"/> Iuda, and a ſure token that their deſtruction was at hand, when the peoples eares began to be <hi>Vncircumciſed, when they could not patiently harken to the truth; and when the word was to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a reproch, &amp; that they could not delighte in it.</hi> If the ſame to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens may be now any way á ſigne to England of her deſtruction, as it was to Ieruſalem, then may Englands Muſicke, be well turned into Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dahes mourning, and ſay,<hi>Woe bee vnto me, Woe is me now,</hi> My heart, my health, my hope, my helpe and all is gon from me. It were a lamentable thing, that our wilfull and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſinnes, (dayly crying for vengeance to fall vpon vs, from the ſeate of God,) our couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vſurie, drunkenneſſe, whordome, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, periurie; contentions, pride, enuie, &amp; diſobedience, ſhould giue our Corne to be meate for our enemies, and the fruite of our labours, to refreſh ſtrangers, while we our ſelues famiſh: yet thus it hath beene in time, and thus it may bee againe.</p>
            <p>Some thinke there be too many Books, too many Sermons, too much preaching, too much Printing: and I thinke there is too little of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſort. There is no fault found with too much eaſe, too much pleaſure, too much negligence,
<pb facs="tcp:12230:9"/> too much wantonneſſe in behauiour, too much pride in apparell, too much loue to imitate new Apiſh toyes and ſtrange faſhions: we are neuer cloyed with theſe, come as thicke as they can, but the poore diſpiſed word ſounds too oft, &amp; comes too thicke vpon vs. O ſinne, O Sathan, Papiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call enuie ſaith, euery boye is become a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: euerie foole is become a writer. Ioſua en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiouſly murmureth against Eldad and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad, for prophecying in the Tent: The Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <note place="margin">Num. 11. 28 Mark 9. 38. Luke. 9. 48 Iohn. 3. 26.</note> of Iohn, enuied at Chriſt for working of Miracles, but I ſay with meeke Moyſes, I would all the people of God did prophecie, I woulde all were learned, I would all were preachers, I would all were ſo perfectly taught of God, that euery man were able to preach to himſelfe, to teach and inſtruct himſelfe and his charge in all things, that wee might indeede neede leſſe preaching, and leſſe writing.</p>
            <p>Some woulde haue no Bookes written, but ſuch onely as did wade into the depth of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and contained the marrow, and quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of learning; ſuch as did profoundly han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle deepe points, &amp; ſuttle quiddities of Diuine or Phyloſophicall controuerſies; and ſuch as in a manner ſhoulde ſpeake that which was neuer ſpoken before.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12230:9"/>
            <p> This is the verie pollicie of Sathan, to take from the ſimple people, their greateſt comfort, (next vnto preaching) that they enioy, which is, the reading or hearing, at leaſure times ſome plaine expoſition or familiar Sermon, penned to their capacitie, wherin many and many take great and ſingular comfort, delight and profit. Many there be, that for age, troubles and other occaſions, cannot often come to heare Sermons, where and when they would, which hauing at home ſome good Booke, ſupplies often times the want of a better meanes, to bring them to the knowledge, and loue of God.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not this to patroniſe any lewd, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton or fooliſh Pamphlets, which tend not to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, but rather to deſtruction; neither yet to prefer or compare reading, or writing with preaching, which is the bleſſed, and ordinarie meanes of our ſaluation, but onely to crop the bloſſomes of their proud Enuie, that deſpiſe their weake brothers gifts, in reſpect of theyr own ſurmiſed perfections: &amp; which think, that ſome profit may not redound to the ſimple, by the moſt ſimple gift, that euer was beſtowed of God vpon the moſt ſimple man.</p>
            <p>I deteſt the fantaſtical humor of them that write or publiſh any booke, to hunt for any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
<pb facs="tcp:12230:10"/> praiſe, glorie, or profit to themſelues, and not with a ſingle, and ſimple intent to ſeeke onely the glorie of God, the furderance of the Goſpell; and the knowledge, comfort and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the weake brethren. With this intent and no other, (as he knowes that knowes my hart) I haue perſwaded my ſelf to ſuffer theſe plaine &amp; Countrie notes, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect themſelues to the curious eyes, to the ſharpe conceites, and the quicke iudgements of the learned Readers of this age, not intended or adorned for the learned, but onely vowed and plotted in the loweſt kinde, for the capacitie of the ſimple and ignorant.</p>
            <p>It may bee that I haue ſtudied more, to bee plaine, briefe and perſpicuous, then ſome haue to flie aloft in the miſtie cloudes of rolling elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; be cauſe I ſeeke the edification of the ſimple, not the praiſe of my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould vauntingly flie ſo high, as the wings of fancie would carrie but a meane Schollers reache, I might neither in dutie doe that I ſhould; nor in conſcience, performe that which I would.</p>
            <p>Let the Iaylors and keepers of Priſons in theſe daies, accounte this example the chiefe flower in their garland, that there hath beene
<pb facs="tcp:12230:10"/> ſo honest a man, an vndoubted childe of God found in their Corporation: of whome, I would they would all learne, to be more mercifull and courteous to their poore brethren that are in bands, to conſider the cauſe of their impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: not to hepe miſerie vpon miſerie, but in their puniſhments to ſee the anger of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their owne ſinnes: to bee ſorrie for them that are in Captiuitie, to thanke God for their owne freedome: not to inſult ouer them, whom God hath caſt downe, but in a charitable mind to comfort them that are in heauineſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the wants of the poore and needie, to their powers. So God (with this Iaylor) ſhall bleſſe them with the true knowledge of their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ioyfull ſpirite of regeneration: So ſhall the Lord comfort them in their diſtreſſe, and deliuer them from the priſon and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which their ſins haue deſerued. This is the wourſt I wiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this the Lord graunt them. And ſo I commit thee, gentle Reader, to Gods mercifull protection. From Honiton in Deuon this 30. day of Iune. 1596.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, Hugh Dowriche.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Verſes written by a Gentle<hi>-woman, vpon The</hi> Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors Conuerſion.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:12230:11"/>
            <l> 
               <hi>THe man is bleſt which can indure,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Whoſe hart doth neuer ſlide,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>When for his ſinne, with fierie ſcourge,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>His patience ſhal be tride.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>No daunting feare can once attainte,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>The conſcience that is cleare:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>The wicked waile that haue no faith,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>When dangers doe appeare.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>The rod that doth correct our life,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And ſinfull waies reproue,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Is ſaid, to be a certaine ſigne,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Of Gods eternall loue.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>No tempting tryall from the Lord,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>No griefe or dire annoye,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Can ſeuer once the faithfull hart,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>From Chriſt, his onely ioye.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Though ſinfull fleſh doe oft rebell,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And fancie file our fall,</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:12230:11"/>
            <l> 
               <hi>Yet happie man, that can returne,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When God beginnes to call.</l>
            <l>Though God permit his choſen flocke,</l>
            <l>Sometimes to walke aſtraie:</l>
            <l>Yet ſets he both the times and meanes,</l>
            <l>To wayne them from their waie.</l>
            <l>How long did Paule, with cruell hart,</l>
            <l>The Church of Chriſt moleſt?</l>
            <l>Till called home to ſee the truth,</l>
            <l>His blindneſſe did deteſt.</l>
            <l>How cruell was this Iaylors hart,</l>
            <l>To vex the poore elect?</l>
            <l>Till trembling earth by mightie power,</l>
            <l>His madneſſe did detect.</l>
            <l>The God, that makes the haughtie hils,</l>
            <l>And Libans Cedars ſhake</l>
            <l>When he ſhall take his cauſe in hand,</l>
            <l>Will make the prowdeſt quake.</l>
            <l>To comfort his, that be in neede,</l>
            <l>The Lord is alwaies preſt,</l>
            <l>And all that haps to his elect,</l>
            <l>Is alwaies for the beſt.</l>
            <l>Which in this picture here is ſeene,</l>
            <l>By that, which ſhall in ſew,</l>
            <l>Lord graunt vs grace, when he doth call,</l>
            <l>To frame our liues anew.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:12230:12"/>
               <head>Ad Authorem, amicum <hi>ſuum, vt plura det.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rge, mi: quidnam titubas eundo?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic labor certé, hoc opus eſt,</hi> Catenas</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nocte ſubnigra, miſeré</hi> Recluſis</l>
               <l>Rumpere <hi>tetras.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Siue diuinas,</hi> Calamo, <hi>loquelas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pingis, aut ſacrum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ore <hi>pandis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Pingis &amp; pandis veneranda, pulchré,</l>
               <l>Dogmata Iouae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hinc, &amp; hinc, laudes (mihi crede) celſae</l>
               <l>Te manent: Sedes manet ampla: vtrin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Digna praeclaris, (quid enim recuſas?)</l>
               <l>Proemia factis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Plura des nobis igitur, Iehouae</l>
               <l>Seruiens, nobis, patriae, tibi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</l>
               <l>Et mihi: Da, quos voluiſſe dix'ti</l>
               <l>Dare, libellos.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:12230:12"/>
               <l>Diuites (Dowrich <hi>per-amice)</hi> Dotes</l>
               <l>Si tui cunctis animi paterent,</l>
               <l>(Pluribus notae:) At taceo tacendi <note place="margin">Apoſiopeſis</note>
               </l>
               <l>Nomen Amici.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ergo, mi: nunquam titubes eundo:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic labor certé, hoc opus eſt,</hi> Cateruas</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quas</hi> Catenatas <hi>tenet atra nigri</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ianua Ditis,</l>
               <l>Soluere vinclis.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Quo pede coepiſti, ſic benè ſemper eas.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Per <hi>Guilielmum Palfraeium,</hi> Gener. Lin-colnienſis Hoſpitij Socium.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <head>
               <hi>Ad Carcerum Cuſtodes.</hi> S. P.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:12230:13"/>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Terrae motu concuſſus, ad vnum,</l>
            <l>Et verum motus, vertitur inde, Deum:</l>
            <l>Quid facis, O Saeuo, ſtringens tua viſcera ferro?</l>
            <l>Sola Saius Animae, quaeritur vna tuae.</l>
            <l>Heu cohibete manus, Cuſtodes Carceris omnes,</l>
            <l>Mittite ſub Chriſti, colla ſuperba Iugum.</l>
            <l>Paule, Comeſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Sila, Captiui corpora; nullas</l>
            <l>Fregiſtis, Domino ſed reſerante, fores.</l>
            <l>Ille aperit vobis, Neopoitae Ianitor aulae,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ac Fletus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vias,</l>
            <l>Et ſoluit duris, religatos crura, cathenis,</l>
            <l>Ad Chriſtum vt properent Liberiore pede.</l>
            <l>Diſcite ab hoc Omnes exemplo, vera vereri</l>
            <l>Numina, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12230:13"/>
            <head>THE IAYLORS Conuerſion.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>PAule and Silas were by the ſpirite of God, ſent into Macedonia, and paſsing through many places of the Countrie, came vnto the chiefe Cittie called Phillippie. Where prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the word, they found a fortune-telling Deuill, which had long time abuſed the ſimple people. Paul not able to beare with this deceite of Sathan, by the word of the Lord expels him. Hereof roſe a grieuous perſecution againſt the word. The worſt part was the greateſt. They preuailed. Paul and Silas were whipt, and caſt into priſon. They praied, and the Lord heard them; and ſent an Earthquake. The Iaylor would haue killed himſelf, but Paul ſtaies him. The Iaylors eyes are opened, he humbleth him
<pb facs="tcp:12230:14"/> ſelfe; he ſeekes the way to be ſaued, he obtaineth it for himſelfe and his whole familie. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <head>THE TEXT.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Actes. 16. 30.</bibl>
                  <q>And he brought them out, and ſaid, Syrs, what muſt I doe, to be ſaued?</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this verſe is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed onely, a queſtion demaunded, by the Iaylor. In which queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion theſe fiue circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. Firſt, The perſon that doeth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde it. Secondly, Of whome he deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it. Thirdly, What the queſtion is which is demaunded. Fourthly, What it was which brought this man to this godly care, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund this queſtion. And laſtly, the time when he fell to this conſideration what hee ought to doe to be ſaued</p>
               <p>For the firſt. In the perſon that doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde the queſtion, theſe three things are to be conſidered. Firſt, his Office. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Charge. Thirdly his ſodden Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. By Office hee was the common Iaylor: which, though it be an Office neceſſarie, yet
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12230:14"/> commonly, I know not how it falleth out, they continue not long honeſt men that haue it; but, for the moſt part, are of nature cruell, hard-harted; and oftentimes blinde and farre from the knowledge of the truth, as this man was.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Application. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> The Lord doth not giue vnto euerie man one order and kinde of life, but hath by a maruailous wiſedome, diſpoſed men, into ſeuerall callings, as they may beſt ſerue for the performance of ſeuerall duties, which are either for order, pollicie, regiment, or the glory of God eſtabliſhed in the Church. And therefore euerie man is to conſider of his calling, and place whereunto hee is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, to acknowledge it to bee the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Lord; to content himſelfe with it, as with a thing deliuered vnto him from the Lorde; to frame himſelfe ſo in it, as hee may onely ſeeke the glorie of God, and not his owne pleaſure, profit, or glorie, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Euerie Office which is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> either commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the worde, or not contrarie to the ſame, is good, lawfull, and honeſt, of it ſelfe in his owne nature: if any Office bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, odious, or lothſome vnto vs, it is made ſo, by reaſon of the wickedneſſe, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, couetouſneſſe, and follie of him that doth poſſeſſe it. As the Publicanes, the Rent gatherers, or Romaine Baylifes made their Office odious among the Iewes, by <hi>Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:12230:15"/> more, then that which was appointed vnto</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 3. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>them.</hi> The ſouldiers made their calling odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, by doing of violence. <hi>Accuſing inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents falſely for their owne luker, Not being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with their wages,</hi> But robbing, ſtealing and ſpoyling beſides. The Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies made their prefeſsion odious, <hi>By their horrible and wicked hypocriſie.</hi> The laylors <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 23.</note> make their Office odious, by vnmercifull abuſing of the poore priſoners, robbing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their great fees, ſelling them but a little libertie for a great deale of money; murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſimple by penurie, by pinching them of their allowance, and ordinarie dutie, and ſuch like, &amp;c. Nay, to fal to a higher recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Kinges and Princes haue made their ſeate and Crowne infamous, by their ſinne and wickedneſſe, as Ieroboam by Idolatrie, <note place="margin">1. King. 12. 28.</note> Ahab and Ieſabel by couetous oppreſsion, ſheding of innocent bloud, and perſecuting Gods Prophets and truth. Dauid by murder and whordome cauſed the enemies of <hi>The Lord to blaſpheme:</hi> Noblemen and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <note place="margin">1. Kin. 21. 8</note> make their degree odious, by their pride, contempt of the word, wantonneſſe, couetouſnes, whordomes, libertie in ſinning, iniurie, and ſuch like. Iuſtices turne iuſtice into wormwoode, and iudgement into gall, condemning the innocent and iuſtifying the wicked, diſhonouring their calling. Lawyers defame their vocation &amp; the godly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12230:15"/> vſe of the law, by taking the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of bad matters, by defiling their hands with bribes &amp; their cloſets with gifts againſt the poore and helpeleſſe, being content for gaine to giue counſell with the wicked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the iuſt, with the mightie againſt the ſimple, with the rich, againſt the poore fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe and widdow, againſt Law, by Law; againſt right, by making ſower ſweete and ſweete ſower, by altering caſes, and making right no right, where it is for their profit, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt conſcience, hauing no conſcience, where commoditie ſhewes it ſelfe. Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue made their neceſſarie and good ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence odious and infamous among the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people and moſt men in theſe daies, by their vntollerable and exceſsiue coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, by taking ſuch great ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for little labour, and oftentimes when to the parties diſeaſed they doe no good at all but rather hurt, without either pietie, pittie or conſcience. Proteſtants and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours <note place="margin">Proteſtants by profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede.</note> of the Goſpell, make the glorious word and preaching of Chriſt to be blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med among the Papiſts, and they hinder many from profeſsing and beleeuing the ſame, becauſe they walke not wiſely toward them that are without: becauſe there is as much whordome, couetouſnes, drunkennes, vſurie, periurie, ſimonie, ſubtiltie, briberie &amp; iniurie amongſt them, as euer was among
<pb facs="tcp:12230:16"/> the Papiſts, or can be among the Turkes and infidels; becauſe there is as little faith, as litle regard of promiſe or word, or leſſe then euer was in the time of ignorance. &amp;c. But what ſhall become of theſe wicked hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, of theſe Painted wals, of theſe ſtinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sepulchers, and fruitleſſe Figtrees, which defame their callings, abuſe their places, pollute their Offices, and diſhonor the Lord by their ſinfull liues: Surely, they ſhall leaue a deadly curſe vpon their poſteritie: the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie mawes of the hungrie Dogges ſhall bee thought to be a Sepulcher, worthie and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for ſuch curſed carrions. The Lorde ſhall plague them by taking from them their ſonne begotten in a dulterie, their Offices, their dignities, and the thing they loue beſt: the Lord ſhall puniſh them by rebellion in in their ſonnes, in their ſubiects, and heauie miſhappes within their owne houſes.</p>
               <p>Some of theſe wicked abuſers of their Office and calling, the Lord doth notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (as we here ſee) cal home to a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of their miſerable eſtate, to the knowledge and ſight of their ſinnes, to a true humiliation of their proude ſtomackes, and to an effectuall repentance, becauſe it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and ſure, that the wickedneſſe of man cannot alter the purpoſe of the Lord. Where we learne, that as God doth ſuffer his elect for a time to be ſeduced, and to wander out
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12230:16"/> of the right way, as Dauid by his luſt, Paule by blinde zeale, Mary Magdalene by lewde concupiſence, and this Iaylor by crueltie &amp; blindneſſe, yet, as many as pertaine to Gods election, haue the times and meanes of their conuerſion appointed, and they, at that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, obey, (as we ſee here this Iaylor doth) though before oftentimes they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed.</p>
               <p>Here we ſee the great mercy of the Lord: which calleth all ſortes of men, which deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth no Office, nor the vileſt callings: which refuſeth not to thinke vppon the greateſt ſinners in the middeſt of all their blindnes, but vſeth louing and fit meanes to call ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to repentaunce. As, according to the qualitie, greatneſſe and continuance of any ſinne, ſo wee ſee his motions to repentance fitted for them. Dauid had not long beene forgetfull, neither remained any great time in the ſincke of his ſinne: therefore the voice of the Lord in a ſimple man wrought a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and repentance in him. Peter had not long continued in his Apoſtaſie, hee was brought vnto that forgetfulnes of his good maſter, and duetie, by the frailenes &amp; feare that was in his fleſh and bloud, and not by any malice or wilfull contempt, therefore the voice of a Cocke was ſufficient to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him, to make him ſee the foulenes of his finne, and to lament his weakenes with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:12230:17"/> teares. But of the contrarie, where the ſinne is ſetled of a long continuance, where the ſinners after admonition haue taken de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite in it, haue continued it with mallice, and wilfull contempt, there, the Lord muſt vſe great and mightie motions to remoue them, as Earthquakes, throwing downe ſome tower in Siloe, ſtirring vp great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and ſhewing great and vnuſuall won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, &amp;c. And yet theſe great motions moue not all, for there are ſome which pertaine to the Lords inheritance, that are conuerted by them, as this Iaylor and many other. But ſuch againe as bee none of this number, but thoſe whome the Lord hath forſaken, and caſt off, cannot be moued nor conuerted by all the ſignes, wonders and Earthquakes that can bee ſhewed: ſuch were the Scribes and Phariſies the maſters of this Iaylor, ſuch was Pharao, ſuch were the ſonnes of Elie, and many in Ieruſalem: ſuch are our great and grounded Papiſts, ſuch are our libertine profeſſors, and fleſhly Goſpellers, ſuch are our Atheiſts and Ieſters in religion, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="charge">
                  <head>2. <hi>His Charge.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>It ſeemeth, that his Charge was very great and that it ſtoode greatly vppon him, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore againe ſuch as he had receiued. It ſhuld appeare that theſe Apoſtles were deliuered vnto him, with ſuch a ſtraite commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that, if he did let them eſcape, his life
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12230:17"/> ſhould go for theirs. For, being now awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by the ſuddaine ſhaking of the earth, &amp; ryſing out of his bed at midnight in great feare, and comming vnto the priſon and finding the doores open, and thinking aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly that his priſoners had beene fled, in a deſperate minde, determined rather to kill himſelfe, then to ſtand to the curteſie of that ſentence, which his good maſters the enuious Scribes and Phariſies ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce againſt him. Which wicked act, the fearefull and deſperate man had committed in deede, had not Paule by the ſpirit of God in the darke ſeene his intent, and with this ioyfull voice at that inſtant comforted him, <hi>Do thy ſelfe no harme: for we are all here.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Application and Doctrine. </seg>
                     </label> Firſt, by his ſtraite Charge which the Scribes and Phariſies gaue for the keeping of theſe Apoſtles, we learne, with what great heate and hateful mallice, the wicked world with the blind potentates thereof doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the truth, whereſoeuer they ſhall ſee it but once to ſhew it ſelfe, or appeare ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo little, and how loth they are that the meſſengers of this newes ſhould eſcape with life or libertie, when they once come within their fingers. The eſtate of Gods trueth in this world is maruelous and miſerable. For the euerie, murder, whordome, drunkennes, &amp;c, hath alwaies found more friendſhip in it, and hath beene better alowed of then the
<pb facs="tcp:12230:18"/> ſimple truth. There was a theefe and a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer preferred before Chriſt himſelfe. The illuſion of Sathan, and a Deuill that decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them, by blinde toyes and telling of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, was a great deale better accepted in this blinde Cittie of Phillippie, then Paule and Silas the true preachers. For wherefore were Paule and Silas caſt into priſon with ſo ſtraite a commaundement, after they had beene buffeted and whipt moſt cruelly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Surely the holy Ghoſt layeth downe no other cauſes but theſe. Firſt, They prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the truth, and aſſayed to turne them from their Idolatry &amp; blindneſſe. Secondly, They caſt out the Deuill that did deceaue them. Where wee learne how vnwilling the world and the wicked are to haue the Deuil caſt out of themſelues, of their ſonnes and daughters, eſpecially if the Deuill bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kinde of commoditie with him, as this Deuill did. For that was the cauſe of this commotion, becauſe Paules new doctrine could not agree with their olde Deuill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they might not follow Paules Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet ſtill retaine their former profite and commoditie. By which we ſee, how hard a matter it is to plant the true Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the couetous and worldly minded wretches. Wee ſee now the cauſe, why the godly in the primatiue church, why the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed martyrs in Queene Maries daies, were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12230:18"/> vexed, exiled, whipped, impriſoned, ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the rackes, tyed and chained to the ſtakes and burned: onely for this, becauſe they preached truely the Goſpell of Chriſt which Paule and Silas preached before: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they called them from darkeneſſe to light, from error to truth, from hell to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: becauſe they opened the illuſions of the Maſſe, Purgatorie and other ſuch peeuiſh fantaſies. But here a man might ſaie, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that there was ſome other matter which moued theſe rulers to lay vp Paule and Silas with ſo ſtraite a charge. For as there was no commoditie came to the rulers by the ſpirit of Diuination which was in the woman, but rather a priuate gaine to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that were her maſters, ſo there was no ſuch hurt like to inſue vnto the Magiſtrate or ſtate of the towne, by expelling of him, as ſhould force them to ſo great a furie: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ther was belike ſome other matter. No, but here we ſee moſt notably<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the nature of the wicked. For it falleth out many times, <note place="margin">The natu of the wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked.</note> that the Magiſtrate which feareth not God, perſwadeth himſelfe that by pollicie, and maintaining of that which beſt liketh the multitude, the common-wealth ſhal be both better &amp; longer maintained quiet &amp; peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, then by eſtabliſhing any thing bee it neuer ſo good, which the people like not. That was one error of the Magiſtrates. An
<pb facs="tcp:12230:19"/> other thing that we ſee in them is, vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and a deſire to keepe their dignitie. Which thing where ſo euer it doth enter, it makes them vnwilling to heare of any alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, bee they neuer ſo little or neuer ſo good, and bee they themſelues neuer ſo full of imperfections, for feare, leaſt if they ſhould alow the doctrine of the Goſpell, in the reformation of one thing, bee it neuer ſo little, it would in time grow farder, and at length perchance finde a fault in their owne beſt cootes that had neede to be amended. That was the cauſe which made theſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſtop the proceedings of the trueth in the firſt appearing, and to alow and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage wicked men in their furie againſt the ſame, when as (if they had done well) they ſhould haue corrected the couetous abuſe of the Deuill: and haue praiſed the good men that did open it, &amp; haue thanked God that had reuealed this abuſe vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Here we ſee another abuſe and follie, that was in thoſe Magiſtrates, for they preſently vpon the cry &amp; exclamation of two or three lewd fellowes without examination of either cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or parties, ſent good men to the priſon, and let the varlets goe vnpuniſhed. Laſtly, we ſee the dulnes and blindnes of ſuch Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates whome the Lord doeth not bleſſe. They could not ſee the right cauſe of this tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult, which was, a couetous minde; neither
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12230:19"/> could they perceiue the pollicie of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, in ſhadowing this cauſe. For the wicked come not to the Magiſtrate &amp; ſay, Sir, they by their preachings haue taken awaye our gaine and commoditie, for then it might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily haue bene perceiued from whence their heate proceeded, but they colour their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe with an other ſhadow, and ſaie: Sir, <hi>Theſe men,</hi> which are Iewes, trouble our Cittie: They preach ordinances which are not lawfull for vs to receiue, neither to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, ſeing we are Romaines. So, we ſee that it is a common thing to intitle that trueth (which we think will in time ouerthrow our pride, &amp; our couetouſnes) with rebellion, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, &amp; conſpiracy: by that menes to make it a cloke for lewdnes &amp; knauerie. Now we ſee the cauſes of this ſtraite charge which the Magiſtrates gaue vnto the Iaylor.</p>
                  <p>We learne here againe, that the Lord ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth euen his elect &amp; choſen for a time to run in the path of ſinners, that he doth exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe them with great temptations, &amp; that he brings them euen to the brincke of hell and deſperation, &amp; yet recals them, &amp; euen then when they are fardeſt gon, &amp; leaſt thinke of ſuccour, then is the Lord neereſt vnto them, as is here to be ſeene by the example of this woefull Iaylor, and many other ſuch like in the Scripture. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Abraham had hoped beyond hope, &amp; had waited for the promiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:12230:20"/> till it was paſt both mans helpe and hope, yet then did the Lord keepe promiſe when he leaſt thought it. When the ſame Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <note place="margin">Gen 17. 19 &amp; 21. 2. Heb. 11. 11.</note> (being commanded to offer vp his ſon that he had ſo long loked for,) could ſee no reaſon of the Lords promiſe, yet at the very <note place="margin">Gen. 22. 10. Eccl. 44. 20.</note> inſtant when the axe was lifted vp, vnknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to Abraham, there was a meanes proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſaue the childe, ere the Axe fell. When there was but a ſily basket betweene death and Moſes, yet at an inſtant, the Lord <note place="margin">Exod. 2. 3. 4</note> had prouided an vnknown meanes, to make him ruler of his people. When Ioſeph was in great extremitie, ſolde into a ſtraunge <note place="margin">Gen. 41. 40.</note> countrie, and for a long time in grieuous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, without friends, or hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and therefore might haue beene comfortleſſe, yet the Lorde, when Ioſeph thought leaſt of it, ſet him at libertie, and <note place="margin">1. Sam. 23. 27.</note> made him ruler of a great Countrie. When Dauid was in great perill by Saule: When Daniel was caſt into the Lyons denne: When the three young men that would not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Idoll, were caſt into the hote fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, <note place="margin">Dan. 6. 22. &amp; 3. 25.</note> yet the Lord at that inſtant when fleſh and bloud coulde ſee no helpe, preſerued them. So, this feare, which the Iaylor felt, firſt in the Earthquake, next in that hee thought that his priſoners had beene al gon, ſtroke him verie deepe to the heart, and brought him to great extremitie, which all,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12230:20"/> vnknowing to him, was vſed by the Lorde, to be a meane of his conuerſion, and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Where wee ſee, how the Lord watcheth ouer his electe, to comfort them, to keepe them, to defend them from water, from fire, from wilde beaſtes, and from deſperation and cruell enemies, that nothing may hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them from that happie hower, wherein the Lord hath appointed to call them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them, and ſaue them.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, wee learne that they bee happie, though they feele ſome miſerie, which may heare the voice of the Goſpel and true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers: for they euer bring comfort and ioye vnto them, that can heare them, they expell all feare, abandon all qualmes of lothſome deſperation, from their heartes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but more happie are they that heare, obey, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues and their affections to the rule of the worde, ſpeaking to their eares outwardly, or of the ſpirite of God, mouing their hearts inwardly, as this Iaylor did.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="alteration">
                  <head>Thirdly, his ſudden Alteration.</head>
                  <p>The Alteration of this man was ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and maruelous. For he, which at the beginning of the night, did with ioy receiue theſe priſoners, with crueltie and diſdaine no doubt thruſt them into the vileſt dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſet them into the ſtockes, and clapt giues vpon their feete: before the ſame night was ended, felt the power and ſpirite of God;
<pb facs="tcp:12230:21"/> confeſſed his ignorance; ſaw his owne ſinne, vnderſtoode the vanitie of his maſters, the Scribes and Phariſies, perceiued himſelfe to bee in an error, humbled himſelfe to them, whom before he had abuſed, and with teares ſought their comfort, whom he thought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be comfortleſſe, deſiring of them to know the right way to bee ſaued, whome a litle before he had condemned as thoſe that helde ſome wrong opinions, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Applicati∣on and Doctrine. </seg>
                     </label> Firſt we ſee, that though God ſuffered his elect, his ſeruants, his truth, by tyrants, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and malicious enemies, in our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bee oppreſſed, ouerborne and tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder, yet he neuer leaueth, nor forſak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, but is preſent with them in their priſons, in the ſtockes, in the darke and vg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pits, hee ſitteth with them, hee ſuffereth with them, he comforteth them, he ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them, he heareth their praiers, &amp; when <note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 19. &amp; 145. 18. &amp; 34. 16. Act. 4. 31. &amp; 12. 10.</note> it pleaſeth him to deliuer them, the ſtrongeſt Irons, priſons, and tyrants in the world, ſhall not be able to hold them.</p>
                  <p>And here we are to remember, what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference there is betweene the miſeries that we feele for the cauſe of Chriſt, and the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which are put vpon vs for our owne wickedneſſe. For when we are caſt into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <note place="margin">Act. 11. 4 Mat. 25. 40 Zakar. 2. 8. Ephe. 1. 22. &amp; 4. 13: 15.</note> for Chriſtes cauſe, Chriſt is there with vs, when we ſuffer for him he is grieued with vs, for the head cannot be quiet, if the body
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12230:21"/> be in paine. Theſe haue alwaies ſuch peace and ioye in their conſcience, that ſuffer for the truth, that when they are whipped they reioyce, when they are wounded they are <note place="margin">Act. 5. 4. Gal. 6. 17.</note> not agrieued, when they are tyed to the ſtakes, they triumph in the middeſt of the fire, the ioy of a good conſcience is ſo great, and the earneſt deſire, and aſſured comfort, of the preſent receiuing of that vnſpeakable ioy that will neuer faile, makes the greateſt torments ſeeme euen to fleſh &amp; bloud, either verie little, or no paine at all: knowing aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly that they could not ſuffer for Chriſt, <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 29 Rom. 9. 29. 2. Cor. 4. 10 Luk. 24. 26.</note> except they were thereunto appointed, that they in theſe paſsions might bee made like vnto the ſonne of God. And aſſuring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that aſſone as they be deliuered from the ſtincking priſon of this filthie carkaſſe, their ſoule ſhall be preſently in the hand of <note place="margin">Deut. 33. 3. Wiſ. 3. 1. 2. Tim. 2. 11 Pſal. 116. 15 Apo. 14. 13.</note> the Lord: wher no torment ſhal touch them, &amp; that they ſhal be preſently with Chriſt in his kingdome, with whome, and for whome they haue ſuffered: and their death being precious in the ſight of the Lord, they feele that they are moſt happie of all other, that die in the quarrell of Chriſt. Of the other ſide, they which ſuffer iuſtly, for their thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, murder, whordome or any other like vice, they feele moſt horrible horror of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and torment both of body &amp; mind, being ſeperated from Chriſt and hauing no
<pb facs="tcp:12230:22"/> peace or ioy in their heart by the quietneſſe of a good conſcience, and aſſured truſt in the mercie of God. And therfore many of them in their tormentes and death, lamentably houle without hope, without comfort, being without the companie of Chriſt, and ſo in miſerable deſperation, without eſpeciall grace, oftentimes end a wretched life. Here wee muſt remember that God doth often giue repentant hearts, to ſuch as haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and doe ſuffer for moſt vile offences, of whome we are to iudge the beſt.</p>
                  <p>Wee learne heere, to haue alwaies a ſure hope, and confidence in the Lord, our cauſe being his, that though we alwaies ſee not his power, and will ready to deliuer vs, when our fleſhe doeth deſire it, yet, let vs aſſure our ſelues that hee is with vs, and that hee will helpe and deliuer vs, when he ſeeth his time.</p>
                  <p>We ſee how quickly God can pul downe the pride, and confound the deuiſes of his enemies, &amp; by ſuch meanes as they can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuſpect, nor preuent, and how quickly he can turne the hearts of the wicked and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, to cheriſh and fauour his ſeruantes, and truth if he liſt.</p>
                  <p>We may learne of this Iaylor here a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <note place="margin">The right vſe of Gods iudgments.</note> leſſon, which is, to make our right, and true vſe of the iudgements of God, when we ſee or feele them; which is, that by them we deſcend into a deepe conſideration of our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12230:22"/> owne eſtate, life, and behauiour, and ſee whether theſe iudgements fall not vpon vs for our pride, our wantonneſſe, whordome, murder, ignorance, ingratitude, negligence, contempt of Gods truth, and euil intreating the ſeruants of God: Which all it ſeemeth that this man conſidered, for he feeling the Earthquake, and knowing that it was the hand of the Lord, hee fell preſently to view his life, the damnable eſtate wherein hee ſtoode, and the lamentable miſerie that hee was to fall into, if his life at that inſtant ſhould haue been taken from him. He comes therefore and deſireth the true Phiſicke, not that which comforteth the body, but that which preſerueth the ſoule. <hi>What ſhall I doe, that I may be ſaued?</hi> How many of vs in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land either high or low, haue with our ſelues entered into this conſideration, hauing felt the like Earthquakes and many other ſignes and tokens? I doubt not, but there be ſome which haue, though it be, perchance, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſome. In all Philippie the Scripture maks mention but of a few which were conuerted thoroughly, and made to ſee, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their ſinne. Wee reade that the rulers were moued, but this motion proceeded not ſo farre, as to make them to ſee the eſtate wherein they ſtoode. Therefore we ſee that the ſignes and wonders of the Lord are not effectuall, in all, but onely in ſuch, as are his,
<pb facs="tcp:12230:23"/> and were before known in his purpoſe. The cauſe of this defect is not in the iudgements themſelues, but in the hardnes, and ſinne of their froward hearts that ſee them: as, the cauſe why a blinde man taketh no comfort of the ſunne, is not in the ſunne it ſelfe, but in the fault of his owne eyes. It may be that many of our Rulers, our great men and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen were at that preſent when they felt Gods hand ſhaken vppon them, in the laſt Earthquake moued, and troubled in minde, but it was ſuch a motion, as the proude Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies felt, which was not ſo ſoone &amp; ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceiued, but it was euen as ſoone and ſuddenly forgotten. It was not ſuch a moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the Iaylor here felt, which made him ſee his ſinne, his imperfections, his wicked life, and rayſed in him a hartie repentaunce for the ſame, and which cauſed him to giue ouer all other cares, as one now wholly mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, to ſeeke onely the right way, how he might be ſaued. For, this motion of the Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, had the ſpirite of the holy Ghoſt ioyned with it, which moued inwardly, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, the heart, with the outward motions of the body: the other, moued but the outward limbes, and ſences, with a ſuddaine fleſhly feare, without the ſpirite of God. For, let vs ſee, how many great men, gentlemen &amp; rich men, which before that time were whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, adulterers, vſurers, theeues, pirats,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12230:23"/> rackers of rents, and and vnmerciful to their poore tenants, how manye that were ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, blaſphemers, Athieſts of no Religion, neither hote nor colde, wantons, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, haue beene ſithens ſoundly conuerted, haue taken an accounte of their liues, of their behauiours, of their ſinnes, and haue repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hartely for them, and haue come vnto their Preachers and Miniſters to learne the right way to be ſaued, and haue euer ſithens continued in that godly courſe, which all, we ſee this Iaylor did? I know not what other preachers can teſtifie, but, for my ſelfe, I can witneſſe but of a verie few, or rather none. There were in ſome fewe places, ſolemne &amp; generall faſtes, by the Paſtors proclaimed, many did reſorte, from manye places, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance many, for the noueltie of the matter more then for any touch of conſcience: but the follie of ſome, the great hypocriſie of a number, the ſhort continuance of the good mind, the quicke forgetting of theſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the murmuring of manye againſt theſe proceedings: doe argue plainely, that the beſt of vs all were farre from the perfect inioying of that ſweete motion, which cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this Iaylor to a ſorrowfull repentance, and kept him alwaies in a perfect obedience. If we conſider this, we may lament, that the Lord in 38. yeares peace and preaching of the Goſpel, hath not by his grace giuen vnto
<pb facs="tcp:12230:24"/> vs ſo perfect harts, and ſorrowfull conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of our ſin, neither ſuch deſire to ſeeke him, nor ſuch obedience to heare him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue him, and continue with him, as at a ſuddaine hee gaue then vnto this poore and miſerable Iaylor, but now a happie and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful belieuer. God graunt that we now ſeeing our want, our imperfections, and our blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which is the curſe of God vppon our ſinne, may with this Iaylor be perfectly, (by the ſpirite of God) moued, vpon the ſight of our ſinne, to true repentance, to humble hearts, to an earneſt deſire to ſeeke our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in Chriſt, that ſo we may continue in perfect obedience to the worde of life, and vnder the protection of Chriſt, eſcape thoſe plagues, miſeries, warres and calamities, which our ſinne, rebellion and vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doe now threaten to pull vpon vs.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, this Iaylor receiued no comfort, ioye, or peace of conſcience, vntill hee was moued by the ſpirit of God, to loue &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the preachers of the word, to heare the voice of the Goſpell, and yeelde obedience vnto the ſame: ſo we learne, that we which are ſicke, are not to hope for health; we that are weake, are not to looke for ſtrength, and we that are wicked, are not to promiſe vnto our ſelues pardon, and forgiueneſſe, vntill, we haue with ſorrow confeſſed, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged our ſickneſſe, weakeneſſe and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12230:24"/> and haue ſought helpe at the Lord, and his word, and haue freely and willingly ſubmitted our rebelling affections to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and direction of the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="circumstance">
                  <head>The ſecond circumſtance. Of whom he demaunded this question.</head>
                  <p>Hee came to the poore Apoſtles. The keeper, to his priſoners, a free-man; to them that were in bondage; he that before thoght well of himſelfe, vnto men that were deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp;c. For now out of all queſtion, hee knew aſſuredly, that they were the ſeruants of God and preachers of the truth. Which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion he had conceiued, by this ſtrange and wonderfull miracle, which GOD for their ſakes had lately wrought. It may be marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, why he feeling his conſcience ſore bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened, with feare, ſorrow, griefe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of ſinne, had not gon for comfort and conſolation vnto the great Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies: which before had taught him. Surely, the ſpirit of God had ſecretly made him to ſee, that they were all blinde guides, that they were farre out of the right way, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now at length was well content to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them all, and to yeelde vnto the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt truth, which at this time appeared plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and would no longer wilfully ſtoppe his eares and refuſe the proffered grace. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, hee did maruelouſly diſgrace the whole company of the Prieſts, Scribes &amp; Doctors,
<pb facs="tcp:12230:25"/> in that hee preferred theſe mens learning counſell and doctrine, before all theirs. Theſe being poore men, ſtraungers and in the outward ſhew of the world abiects: and the other, men rich, glorious, graue, and in the opinion of moſt men, learned, and great Rabbies. Beſides all this, he put him ſelfe in great daunger of excommunication, of life and liuing, which they had publiſhed againſt <note place="margin">Io. 9. 23, 34.</note> all ſuch as ſhould enter either acquaintance or familiaritie with them which ſpake or taught in the name of Ieſus, whom they had crucified. Yet we ſee, that hee caſting away all feare and not conſulting with fleſh and <note place="margin">Gala. 1. 16.</note> bloud, ſubmitted himſelfe happyly to bee a Scholer vnto theſe Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Application. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                     </label> Firſt we learne, in our extremities, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, feare, doubts, &amp; heauie trouble of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, where we are to ſeeke for eaſe, helpe and comfort: not of the blinded, proude, and cruel Phariſie, which is not acquainted with the motions of Gods ſpirit: but of the pure word of God, reuealed, and preached vnto vs, and of the true preachers and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, which leade vs directly to Chriſt &amp; no other. When we will take comfort by the word, we muſt not conſult with the Papiſts <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Torrenſis in confeſſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtiniana. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Houſius de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſo verbo.</hi>
                     </note> the Iudaſites, terming themſelues Ieſuites for they will tell vs, that the Scriptures are hard and obſcure, and that it is but loſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to reade them, &amp;c. But the ſpirite of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12230:25"/> God, in the Scripture, teacheth vs the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, that the worde of the Lord is a light <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. Prou. 6. Eſay. 45. Iohn. 6. 2. Pet. 1.</note> vnto our feete, and a lanthrone vnto our pathes.</p>
                  <p>When wee are troubled with concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the firſt motions of ſinne, the prickes of Sathan in our fleſh, which driue the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to great ſorrow, we may not goe for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Torrenſ. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 2. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thechiſmus ex decret. Conſ. Trident. in Sacra. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</hi>
                     </note> and remedy, vnto the Phariſaicall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, for hee will goe about to perſwade vs, that this <hi>Concupiſence, and the firſt motions</hi> are no ſinne in their owne nature, neither any ſinne at all, either in name, or ſubſtance, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Conſent</hi> go with it: which deuiliſh voice, and lie, is confuted by the word of God, for it is called <hi>Enmitie against God,</hi> it is againſt the commaundement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not lust or couet,</hi> It confirmes their horrible ſin, which <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 7. Exod. 20. 17 1. Iohn. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Mat. 5. 22.</note> ſay <hi>They haue no ſinne: Chriſt</hi> accountes the motion of anger a deadly ſinne, and worthie iudgement. Laſtly the definition of ſinne by Saint Iohn confutes them. <hi>Sinne is the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3. 4</note> 
                     <hi>of the law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Litle comfort ſhall the weake younglings finde in them, which ſay, that the Scripture is not ſufficient for their ſaluation, but they muſt ſeeke other traditions: which ſay, that to belieue in Chriſt is not ſufficient, except he keepe the whole law: which impudently and wickedly affirme, that Chriſt by his death hath not ſufficiently purged their ſins
<pb facs="tcp:12230:26"/> but that there is an other Purgatorie, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to clenſe, and make cleane the faithfull, <note place="margin">Col. 2. 8.</note> thorough which, euery one muſt paſſe, that ſhall enter into heauen. Contrarie to the preaching of the true Apoſtles, and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred word, for wee are bid to take heede of <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 14</note> mens traditions, that wee bee not deceiued by them. Againe, that wee follow not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of men which turne from the truth. And in the very next verſe to my text, <note place="margin">Act. 16. 31.</note> Paule tolde this Iaylor that it was ſufficient both for him and his houſholde to be ſaued <note place="margin">Ioh 3. 18. &amp; 5. 24.</note> if he did onely belieue: Chriſt hath ſaid. <hi>He that belieueth ſhall be ſaued, Hee that belieueth in the ſonne ſhall not come into iudgement: Hee</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Wiſd. 3. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>that heareth my word, and belieueth in him that ſent me, hath life euerlasting, hee ſhall not bee iudged, but hath paſſed from death vnto life.</hi> The ſoules of the righteous are in the hands of God, and no torment ſhall touch them. <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 3.</note> Chriſt by himſelfe hath purged our ſinne, therefore we neede no other Purgatories, &amp; we defie ſuch as haue inuented them to the derogation of Chriſts power and honour.</p>
                  <p>Litle comfort may a wounded conſcience <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Torrenſis. lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. ca.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Conſilium Tridenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>um ſeſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>an.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3. <hi>&amp; can.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.</note> find at their hand who teach, That men muſt alwaies doubt, and neuer aſſure themſelues of their election in Chriſt, what motions ſo euer they feele, and that they muſt alwaies carrie an vncertaine opinion, whether they ſhall perſeuere vnto the end, or not. But let
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12230:26"/> them come to the pure fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine of the word of God, and then they ſhall heare the ſpirite <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 7.</note> tell them, that, except they belieue the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of ſinnes,</hi> without doubting, or if they wauer vncertainely in doubtfull dumpes, they ſhall neuer obtaine anye thing of the <note place="margin">Mat. 9. 2.</note> Lord: they ſhall heare Chriſt ſay, Son, ſtand not in doubt, but comfort thy ſelfe &amp; aſſure thy ſelfe, Thy ſins are forgiuen thee. They ſhall heare, that Abraham after the promiſe was made vnto him, neuer doubted of the <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 18. 19</note> performance of it, not conſidering himſelfe, and the weakeneſſe of his owne body, but the promiſe, and the abilitie of the Lorde that had promiſed. They ſhall heare the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God tell the Corinthians, and vnder them, vs, that we being ſometime diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent (hauing now receiued and belieued the word) <hi>Are ſanctified, are iustified in the name</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and by the ſpirite of our God.</hi> They ſhall heare Paule in the full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of his election, to reioyce without doubting, I <hi>liue, yet not I now, but Chriſt liueth in me, and in that, that I now liue in the fleſh, I</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gala. 2. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, by the faith in the ſonne of God, who hath loued me, and giuen himſelfe for me.</hi> They ſhal heare the ſpirite exhorting them to go bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 16. &amp; 10. 19.</note> to the throne of grace, and not to doubt, but rather, that by the bloud of Chriſt they may be bolde, &amp; truſt perfectly (not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly) <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 13.</note> on the grace that is brought vnto
<pb facs="tcp:12230:27"/> them, &amp;c. Aske of the Papiſts, which teach this doubting doctrine, what is ment by that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or fulneſſe of faith, whereof the Scripture makes ſo much mention, calling it the full <hi>Aſſurance of vnderſtanding, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Col. 2. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>faith?</hi> they muſt needs if they anſwere truely, ſay, that it is <hi>A peculiar</hi> application, <hi>whereby euerie perfect beleeuer, that feeleth the earneſt pennie of his election, doth applye vnto</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 1. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>himſelfe, the promiſe of eternall life in Christ Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now for perſeuerance vnto the end, of which the Papiſts would haue vs to doubt, Let them conſider whether they ſaye not daily in their beliefe, <hi>I belieue euerlaſting life.</hi> If they doe, let them conſider what they be that Chriſt ſaith ſhall be ſaued. <hi>They that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to the end. Such as be not werie in weldoing.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 13. 2. The. 3: 13</note> Then, if they belieue that any ſhal be ſaued, they muſt needes alſo belieue that they ſhal endure to the end. So that they muſt needes confeſſe, that the faithfull ſhall indure vnto the end, ſuch I meane, as are appointed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. And if this argument ſuffice not, let vs ſee, what ſpeeches the full aſſurance of this perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto the end, hath brought forth in the elect and godly. Dauid ſayth. Doubtleſſe, <hi>goodnes and mercie ſhall follow me</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 23. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>all the daies of my life, &amp;c.</hi> Paule ſaith, <hi>I am perſwaded that neither death nor life, &amp;c. ſhall ſeperate vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue of God which is in Chriſt</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 38.</note>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:12230:27"/> 
                     <hi>Ieſus our Lord.</hi> Againe, the ſame Paule ſaith, vnto ſuch as afterwarde had receiued the word, and belieued in this Cittie of Phillip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie where our Iaylor was, I <hi>am perſwaded</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>that he which hath begun this good work in you, will performe it vntill the day of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Thus we ſee that wee are to comfort our ſelues in this, that if wee pertaine vnto Chriſt, we may not doubt of our election, or perſeuerance, which both we muſt be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of; not by reaſon of any perfection, ſtrength, or goodneſſe in our ſelues; but onely, relying on the might, and mercie of Ieſus Chriſt, which by his bloude hath redeemed our dayly, and fleſhly imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and fals, that our continuaunce in him, and by him, may neuer be finally bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off.</p>
                  <p>Thus we ſee to whome we muſt goe with this Iaylor for comfort in our extremitie, &amp; whome we muſt auoide.</p>
                  <p>We ſee further, that GOD hath at all times confirmed his trueth, ſpoken by his ſeruants, with manifeſt ſignes, and tokens, whereby they that were not quite forſaken, might bee called to the knowledge of the ſame. What good our ſignes and tokens haue done to vs, I can not ſee, but onely, that manye, by them are made the more hard harted, and careleſſe, no doubt to their farder condemnation.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12230:28"/>
                  <p> This Iaylor no ſooner ſaw the power of God, making manifeſt and giuing teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vnto the truth, which the Apoſtles had preached, but he preſently yeelded vnto it, imbraced it, ſought his remedie by it, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke his olde cuſtomes, and maſters, &amp; was content and willing to learne. He no ſooner ſaw the iudgements of God, but ſtraight he remembred his ſinne, he repented, hee bad farwell to his former delightes, pleaſures, paſtimes, wantonneſſe, and wickedneſſe, and of an enemie, became a friend, of a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, a profeſſor, of a proude maſter, an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruant, and of a ſinfull Iaylor a penitent beleeuer. Therefore as Chriſt ſaid, that Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus and Sidon, and the Queene of the South ſhould riſe in iudgement, againſt the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harted vnbelieuers of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo no doubt, this Iaylor as he condemned the proud Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies then, ſo, he ſhal be a heauie condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to our blinde Papiſtes and our carnall and licentious profeſſors of the Goſpel, now, which hauing the truth, haue loued error more then the truth: hauing the light, haue deſired darkeneſſe more then the light, and hauing ſaluation offered by Chriſt, haue choſen rather damnation, in following their owne deuiſes, and wilfully continuing the courſe of their ſweete olde ſinnes, For our Papiſts, notwithſtanding all the preaching of Chriſt, will be ſtill Moſes Diſciples, they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12230:28"/> wil not forſake the cuſtomes of their fathers, and the ignorance of that time, wherin they were Chriſtened, they will neuer ſuſpecte that there can bee hypocriſie, error and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite vnder the graue habites, and demure countenances, of their old Doctors, Prieſts, Scribes and Phariſies. They would be loth to depart from the vnitie (as they call it) &amp; the conſent, of ſo many ages, counſels, and learned fathers, to belieue the new doctrine of Paule and Silas, ſtrangers, wanderers, but lately heard of &amp; but euen now come to the towne. Theſe, and many other ſtops, were laide in the laylors way, to haue kept him from obedience to the truth, but, when the arme of the Lord was reuealed vnto him, and when by the ſpirite of God his hart was <note place="margin">Act. 16. 14.</note> opened, he caſt of theſe fantaſtical ſhadows, and obeyed the effectuall calling. He might haue aleaged againſt the Apoſtles, euerye way, as much as any Papiſt in the world can ſay, againſt the Goſpell, and the Lords in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, which in this laſt age, hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, and appointed to vnrake the truth from the dull aſhes, and miſties ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, in which it lay long time for ſinne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed, the worlde being not worthie of it. Now the Papiſtes muſt condemne this Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, to be a foole for conſenting ſo quickly to ſtrange doctrine, for giuing credit to a fewe againſt many; to ſtrangers, againſt men that
<pb facs="tcp:12230:29"/> were knowne, and for reuolting ſo eaſilye from the faith wherein hee was baptiſed: or, if they will not condemne him, whome the word doth commend, they muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne themſelues, for not belieuing the ſame worde, and obeying the like callings. Eſpecially, ſeeing they haue many and diuers other examples, that vrge and teach the ſame, as, Eliſha, who ranne after Elias vpon a <note place="margin">1. King. 19 20.</note> ſmall calling, to our iudgement: The Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples alſo vpon ſmal acquaintance were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to forſake, ſhippes, nets, occupation, <note place="margin">Mat. 4. 18.</note> gaine, friendes and father, to follow Chriſt, aſſone as hee called them. Mathew being a Publican was content, at one word, to ariſe, to leaue his Office, his profit, his glorie, his maſters and former teachers, to follow an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Mat. 9. 9.</note> maſter that had now called him. What ſhould I recken Paule, Cornelius, Lidia, with infinite others, which obeyed the ſame calling that our Iaylor did. Surely, if the like ſhould happen now, if any ſhould fall away from Poperie, from ſuperſtition, to follow Chriſt, or belieue the doctrine of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: if Eliſha, if the Diſciples, if Paule, if Cornelius, now liued, they ſhould bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Pope, to be raſh, fooliſh and rancke heretiques. It is time for vs which haue beene ſo long and many waies called, at length to bid farwell vnto your pleaſures, delightes, deceite, hypocriſie, &amp;c. This
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12230:29"/> Iaylor will riſe in iudgement againſt vs.</p>
                  <p>The Popiſh chaine of vniuerſalitie, was now not yet coyned, or of this man little eſteemed; which, at this time, is one of the great Ankers, which holdes the Popedome that it ſinckes not, and keepes ſo many ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fooles in bondage, vppon great bragges and vaine oſtentation; of a Monſter in the ayre, which neuer was, That all the worlde (forſoth) is of their Religion; or was not long ſithens. If this be true, where was then, I ſay, not the popiſh vniuerſalitie, (for that hath alwaies beene an vniuerſalitie of error,) but where was any vniuerſalitie of the truth, at all, when firſt the linage of Seth; then of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, and his kindred, in all the world, Iſrael, among all nations: onely Iuda, among all the tribes, onely Iohn Baptiſt in al Iudea, Chriſt only and his Apoſtles in all the earth, Paul &amp; Silas only in all Macedonia, Luther and a few others in all Germanie, gaue teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the truth? Had it not beene a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh thing for this Iaylor to haue ieſted at the truth, becauſe there were but a few that profeſſed it? Euen ſo groſſe an abſurditie it is now, in our Papiſts to ſay, that we haue not the truth, becauſe, it is not vniuerſally cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, and belieued of all men, and in al pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces receiued, when as it is certaine, that the truth hath neuer beene vniuerſally recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, nor euer will: but rather it hath alwaies
<pb facs="tcp:12230:30"/> beene (by the wicked, and moſt part of the world) vniuerſally perſecuted, and kept vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſo will continue, till the daye of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>We ſee, that if the opinion of wiſedome, grauitie, and learning; if gray haires, ſtrange formes of apparell, with braue and gorgeous ſhewes: if the riches, pompe, pride, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the world, in the dumbe Scribes and Phariſies, could haue pacified the troubled conſcience of this poore man, hee needed not to haue come to the Apoſtles. But wee learne, that though error, and the illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Sathan, bare a gallant face, and delightfull countenance, outwardly to the world, to blind, and deceiue the ſences of the ſimple, yet there is nothing can pacifie, (with true peace) the conſcience wounded for ſinne, but onely the word of God. For I pray you, what is he, in all the time of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that can ſay, that he was either comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in conſcience, or conuerted from ſinne, by any of the masking ſhewes in apparel, by the melodie, ſencing, perfuming, images, painting, guilting, croſsing, ſhriuing, or any other ſuch Apiſh toyes, vſed for a pompe, without preaching or expounding the word? Saint Paule alowes not any thing to be vſed, neither by the miniſter, nor in the Church, <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 2. 1. Tim. 1. 4. 1. Cor. 14. 26. 40.</note> but ſuch things onely, as concerne a godly decencie, and are knowne to edifie.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:12230:30"/>
                  <p> Laſtly, here is a glaſſe, which neuer failes, to ſhew vs the true proportion, of ſuch as be <note place="margin">A true glaſſe for al eſtats.</note> rightly touched, at the touch-ſtone of Gods ſpirit. We ſee this man after he was touched, how little aſhamed hee was to confeſſe his blindneſſe, to condemne himſelfe, to deſire helpe; how little afraide hee was, to venter credit, office, liuings, life and all to obtaine that ſaluation which he deſired, &amp; of which he now felt the want. This was a ſure token in him, and ſo it is in all, to know them that are rightly called, from the hypocritical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors. For it is as poſsible, that they which be rightly touched, ſhould continue in their olde couetouſneſſe, whordome, drunkennes, blaſphemie, malice, negligence, and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as it is for the ſpirite of God to continue in the heart of a wicked man: which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be. Now we ſee what we are to thinke of thoſe lyars, which ſay with their mouthes, <note place="margin">Wiſ. 1. 3. 4. 5 Titus. 1. 16.</note> they know God, and haue felt his motions, and yet in their deedes denie him: and of thoſe fruiteleſſe and curſed Figtrees, which in the ſpring bud faire and promiſe greate hope and yet at harueſt yeelde nothing but <note place="margin">Mat. 21. 19.</note> leaues, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="circumstance">
                  <head>The third circumſtance. What queſtion it was that the Iaylor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded.</head>
                  <p>The queſtion is. What muſt I doe, to be ſaued?</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12230:31"/>
                  <p> Hee inquires not now, after the faſhion of worldlings, what muſt I doe to come to promotion, to honour and dignitie? What muſt I doe to become rich, and to obtaine an eaſie &amp; quiet life? What muſt I do to be reuenged of my enemies, to deceiue my neighbours, and to ſatisfie my luſt? &amp;c. No he was not troubled about any ſuch matter, but the ſpirite of God had now made him carefull onely for one thing, and the beſt thing, which was, what he might doe to bee ſaued, and to haue his ſinne forgiuen. And it ſeemeth that the iudgements of God had touched him home, that ſo preſently, a man ſo carnall, ſo fleſhly, ſo worldly and ſenſual, ſhould ſo willingly take his leaue of the loue of the world, of the vanities and pleaſures of the ſame, the loue of his houſe, wife, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, liuing, life and all, and onely craue to know that which few did deſire, which many did deſpiſe, that is, what he might do to be ſaued. Pointing as it were with his finger vnto the onely marke, &amp; end, vpon which euerie man ſhould haue his whole care fixed &amp; planted.</p>
                  <p>In this queſtion, wee are to conſider the manner of his comming vnto them, and his ſalutation. He fel down before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, he brought them out, hee called then in Greeke my Lordes, by a reuerend title. What could hee haue done more to Noble men? Nay what could he haue done more to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12230:31"/> the greateſt princes in the world? But a man may aske, how could Paul &amp; Silas abide to be honoured &amp; not reprehend him. Surely, they knew that he honored the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly (which Paul could not abide in other <note place="margin">Act. 14. 14. 15.</note> places, &amp; men,) but rather that he vſed this geſture, forced vnto it, by the manifeſt feele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Act. 10. 26.</note> of the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God in the late Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, and therefore ſuffered him to doe it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Application and Doctrine. </seg>
                     </label> We ſee firſt how the Lord, when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, forceth euen his enemies, in their conſcience to giue that truth an honourable teſtimonie, which they perſecuted, and to honour it with great reuerence.</p>
                  <p>Wee learne of this Iaylor, to honour the Lords gifts, (eſpecially the worde of truth) whereſoeuer we find it, whether it be in the priſon, or at libertie, whether it bee contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or honored, whether it be in men ſimple and deſpiſed, or in men of credite and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For the Lorde chuſeth manye times the weake, to confound the mightie, &amp; the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to ſhame the proude, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>We ſee againe, that the miniſterie of the word, is a calling and Office, ordained, and bleſſed by the Lord, and therefore hee will haue it honored of all men. Becauſe the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters thereof are not the Embaſſadours of worldly Princes, (which is alſo a calling of greate honour, for they repreſent the Maieſtie of the Kinge and are as it were
<pb facs="tcp:12230:32"/> the verie mouth of the Prince himſelfe (but they are the meſſengers of the Prince of all Princes, the eternall Lorde of heauen and earth: they repreſent the maieſtie of the Lord, in his word, and when we heare them ſpeaking (if they preach nothing but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the verie word) wee muſt aſſure our ſelues that we heare the Lord ſpeaking vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in them. Therefore we find that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, the word it ſelfe giues them hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable titles, for S. Paule ſaith, they are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of double honour. This Iaylor heere <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5. 17</note> cals them by the worthieſt name of prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence that he could deuiſe, not in reſpect of their perſons, which ſeemed to bee but ſimple, but for the loue and honour which he bare to the word, which they profeſſed.</p>
                  <p>Another thing we are here to conſider, which may not be forgotten, That, the Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor in demaunding this queſtion, <hi>What muſt I doe to bee ſaued,</hi> flatly and plainely ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes, and condemneth, all the Religion of the Scribes and Phariſies, to bee nothing elſe, but a fardle of ceremonies, toyes, and ſuperſtitions, ioyned with a worldly pompe, and beautie onely, hauing nothing in it to comfort the hart oppreſſed with Woe, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the conſcience of the mercie of God in Ieſus Chriſt, which is the onely Sauiour and ſaluation of the elect by faith. For if hee had beene perſwaded that the doctrine which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12230:32"/> the Phariſies taught concerning the fulfill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the lawe, had beene ſufficient for his ſaluation, &amp; to haue brought him the right way to the mercie of God, and the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſinne, he would neuer haue come vnto the Apoſtles, to haue learned another way, which had beene ſuperfluous. But wee ſee plainly, that he did now not only doubt, but boldly renounce, and abandon and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake in the plaine fielde, the Phariſies ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, the rites, and Religion wherein hee was borne, brought vp, and had for a long time continued. Becauſe hee ſaw that now, when he moſt needed, he could find no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort nor ſaluation in it at all. As if he ſhould ſay: <q>Sirs, I was borne vnder the Religion <note place="margin">The Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Iaylor vnto the Apoſtles.</note> which the Phariſies profeſſe, I haue beene zealous in it, as many others at this day are. I haue had an honorable opinion of it, and haue hated them that haue gain-ſaide it, I haue beene of long time now led with their outward pompe of dumbe ſhewes, &amp; I could neuer by anye meanes bee perſwaded that theſe great, graue, auncient, learned &amp; wiſe men could euer haue bene deceiued, or haue beene conuinced of any error, or ſo blinded, that they could not haue ſene the truth. Yet now, I plainely ſee, that they all, the verye beſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are but hypocrits, blind guides, foliſh, ignorant of the true knowledge, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <note place="margin">Ma, 23. 13</note> &amp; the generation of Vipers, which ſhut
<pb facs="tcp:12230:33"/> vp the kingdome of heauen, and wil neither enter themſelues nor ſuffer others that would, which deuour the widdowes houſes with colour of long praier, which compaſſe ſea &amp; land to make one of their profeſsion, which make cleane the outerſide of the cup and platter, but within are full of briberie and exceſſe, which I ſee are nothing elſe but whited Tombes, full of dead mens bones, &amp; all filthynes, &amp;c. I can not find now in their Religion anye comfort at all for a wounded conſcience, or any hope to haue my ſins for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen. Now therefore ſith it hath pleaſed the Lord with one motion to moue both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and heart, and that he hath made me ſee my ſinne, my ignorance, my blindnes:</q> I doe here forſake, renounce and deteſt for euer, this Phariſaicall ſuperſtition. And ſeeing this courſe that I haue taken, can doe me no good, I pray you, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I now know to be the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the liuing God, &amp; prechers of the truth, Tell mee at length what courſe I muſt take, &amp; what I muſt do that I may be ſaued?</p>
                  <p>By which words wee ſee that he did not only ſuſpect but vtterly by the ſpirit of God renounce that, which the ſame ſpirite had tolde him, to be wicked and abhominable. And I wiſh in perfect charitie that all thoſe which are now blinded with Poperie, and lie yet drunken with the curſed wine of the great whore of Babilon, al what euer they be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12230:33"/> either in Italy, France, Spaine or England, may, (if they pertaine to the Lords election) feele the like motions &amp; the like hartquakes to aſſault their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, &amp; open their eyes, that they may once feele &amp; ſee their blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, their errors, and their ſinnes &amp; certaine damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they may once with this Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor perfectly bid farwell vnto al the Romiſh Phariſies, blind guides, &amp; deceiuing hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, that now ſo monſterouſly abuſe them.</p>
                  <p>Againe, ſeeing this Iaylor ſeekes to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, let vs conſider what ſaluation it is that he deſireth. The Greek word ſignifieth ſuch a kind of ſauing, as that a man may continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally remaine aſſured and without feare. The Syrian Paraphraſe hath it, what muſt I doe that I may liue? Which is as much to ſay, as, to be preſerued: which teacheth vs, that hee ſought not for the temporal &amp; preſent ſauing of his life, the feare of the earthquake being paſſed, and they being that way able to doe him no good, neither did he as the wicked are wont to do, which ſeing the iudgements of God, for a time tremble, &amp; quake, but the rod being paſt, they return againe vnto their former wickednes: But, this man being right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touched, and fearing more his ſin, then the Earthquake, earneſtly ſought for the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſoule, the comfort of which might continue with him for euer. If he deſired the right waye, the verie truth, and life it ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:12230:34"/> whome did he deſire but Chriſt? If hee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">Iohn. 14. 6.</note> ſaluation, what deſired hee but Chriſt, which is the onely Sauiour of the faithfull? Bleſſed, ſaith Dauid, is he whoſe wickednes is forgiuen &amp; whoſe ſin is couered. If no man <note place="margin">Pſalm. 32. 1</note> can bee bleſſed, happie, ioyfull and ſaued, but they that haue their ſins forgiuen: then wee ſee what ſaluation it is that this man ſought, namely, an aſſurance that his ſinnes ſhould be forgiuen, &amp; the meanes by which hee might attaine vnto this. This ſaluation the Phariſies coulde not teach this Iaylor then, and our Papiſtes purely without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption will not haue it taught now.</p>
                  <p>Further, we learne here, if we ſee any cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, wicked, and malicious perſecutors of the truth, or any other abhominable ſinners, not to proceede in raſh iudgement againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne for reprobates, but rather to leaue this iudgment to the Lord, who only know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what they be that are his, becauſe wee know not whether the Lord haue appointed both time and meanes for their conuerſion, as hee had for this Iaylor, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly we learne, that this care and deſire of the Iaylor condemneth the cares and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of many of vs that haue beene longer <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h. 10. 41. 42.</note> taught. Chriſt ſaid once to a worldly minded Martha, Martha, thou careſt &amp; art troubled about many things, but one thing is neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp;c. This one needfull thing is to deſire
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12230:34"/> to heare the worde of God and the meanes how to bee ſaued, and haue our ſinnes forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. This one thing had the Iaylor nowe found, this one thing he deſired &amp; no more. Whoſoeuer therefore neglecting the word of God and care of ſaluation, applyeth his mind to any other exerciſe, pleaſure, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, his care is needleſſe, vaine, fooliſh and wicked. For all our cares, ſtudies and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors, wherin we haue not a principal regard vnto the glorie of God and our owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are accurſed of the Lord, and therefore can neuer bring a bleſsing vppon vs. The counſels and conſpiracies of the wiſe Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophels, <note place="margin">2. Sam. 17.</note> the Lord for his Dauid ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw by his appointed Huſhais. No proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, counſell, or determination for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment or ſafetie of any common-welth, can euer ſtand long, or bring a bleſsing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that land, where the principall marke of all their deuiſes tend not to the eſtabliſhing and ſetting forth of the truth, the honour of God, and ſaluation by Chriſt Ieſus our one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sauiour. Hoſpitalitie is good: a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prouiſion of things neceſſarie, is alowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: an earneſt deſire to bee diligent in our vocations, occupations, and callings, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended: but yet to loue, follow, or be buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo in any of theſe, that we neglect at times conuenient, and when occaſions be offered, to heare the Sermons of Chriſt, or neglect
<pb facs="tcp:12230:35"/> the learning of the knowledge of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is in Martha by Chriſt greatly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. There bee many Marthaes in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land which trouble themſelues about many vaine pleaſures, offices, and deuiſes, while in the meane time they neglect the beſt dutie: As Gentlemen that trouble themſelues to build faire houſes &amp; gorgeous palaces, which yet care not for the building of the Lordes houſe, and as little for their owne ſaluation: countrie men that are careful to prouide for their poſteritie, yet careleſſe for their owne ſafetie and helpe of their ſoules: Miniſters, which either for ignorance, negligence, or contempt of the word, leauing the conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of their calling giue themſelues ſom to be husbandmen, farmers, graſiers &amp;c, ſome to be Phyſitions, Lawyers, and other ſecular officers, as though that one bleſſed calling of theirs were not needful only, &amp; ſufficient, to preach the word of God truely, and to liue thereafter, &amp; to bring the ſimple &amp; ignorant to know which way they muſt be ſaued. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="circumstance">
                  <head>The fourth circumstance. What it was, which brought this man to this Conſideration.</head>
                  <p>The text ſhews vs, that it was the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and hand of the Lord which he felt in the Earthquake, and the holy Ghoſt alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly working which wrought this care &amp; deſire in him, and made him to haue a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of his ſins, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12230:35"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Application and Doctrine. </seg>
                     </label> Firſt we ſee, that it is a profitable &amp; good thing for a man to feel the iudgements, rods and ſcourge of the Lord oftentimes, to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him out of his ſecuritie, and alſo to caſt downe his pride, that he may learne to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf before the Lord. For eaſe, peace, and quietneſſe bring vs a ſleepe, harden our harts, make vs to contemne the meſſengers and worde of the Lord: But feare and his rod when it is ſeene, maketh vs more apt to learne, and willingly to ſeeke for comfort &amp; helpe. Therefore ſaid Dauid, <hi>It is good for me</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 67 71</note> 
                     <hi>that I haue beene afflicted, that</hi> I <hi>may learne thy statuts. For before I was troubled, I went aſtray, but now I keepe thy word.</hi> The worldly mindes which are not indued with ſpirituall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, do wonderfully repine, murmure, and frowne againſt all miſeries, ſickenes, calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, plagues, or what troubles ſo euer hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in this life, deteſting al things which are not pleaſant to the fleſh, as a thing moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to nature. But the godly on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide do know, that the church &amp; ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God in this life, are ſubiect to many croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, troubles, perſecutions, not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Church ſhal periſh w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe afflictions, but rather y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is thus ordained by the ſingular prouidence of the Lord, that by this meanes his ſeruants may ſee their ſins, &amp; the Lords anger againſt it, that they may learne to tame the mad and outragious concupiſcence of the fleſh, &amp; that
<pb facs="tcp:12230:36"/> faith, loue, charitie and mercie, with the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of one anothers infirmities, may dayly increaſe, and bee renewed in them. Where we ſee, that theſe afflictions, are nothing but iuſt corrections for our eſcapes and faultes: and we ſee what they be that are moſt fit to receiue admonition, euen ſuch as are moſt viſited with afflictions, griefes, ſickeneſſe, want of things neceſſarie, and ſuch like, &amp;c. Bleſſed is the man whome the Lord correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, becauſe it is a ſigne of his loue, &amp; bleſſed <note place="margin">Iob. 3. 17.</note> is that man which indureth temptations, &amp; continueth conſtant to the ende, and is not <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 12.</note> ouerborne with calamities, for hee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a Crowne of life, which the Lord hath <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 10.</note> promiſed to them that loue him.</p>
                  <p>Againe; we are to learne, that, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wee ſee the Lord to wounde our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, or to threaten vs with any calamitie, warres, plagues, ſickneſſe, or any other viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, hee doth it for no other cauſe, but to make vs to conſider that we are gon aſtray, that we are out of order, that our life is not ſuch as it ſhould be, and that he hath a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie quarrell, and reckoning againſt vs. Then here we ſee the cauſe, why the Lord hath of late giuen vs ſo many gentle warnings, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vs ſo many louing rods, and like a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full father, hath rather made vs as yet to ſee them, then to feele them. And yet ſurely we haue ſo ſeene the ſentence (as it were) of our
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12230:36"/> own condemnation, in ſignes in the heauens, and wonders in the earth, in Earthquakes, in the neceſsitie, &amp; crie of many thouſands in this time of miſerie, by the ſtop of mutual traficke, and euen now in theſe rumors of warres, and expectations of forraine inuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: that we may eaſily coniecture, what ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect there will follow, if the cauſe be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued. Our ſinne, our vnthankefulnes, our negligence, our careleſſe and licentious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, in all eſtates, our wicked behauiours, our monſterous apparell, our want of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, loue and patience, our aboundance of enuie, malice, deceite, whordome, and like abhominations, are the cauſes of theſe tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, of theſe motions, of theſe feares, and of theſe ſignes and tokens. And, if wee with this Iaylor bee not drawne, by ſome meanes to ſeeke helpe the ſooner, wee are to looke for ſome heauie miſery to fal vpon vs &amp; our land. The Lord ſhakes theſe rods ouer our heads to ſome purpoſe, wee muſt thinke. A carefull &amp; louing father, if he find his childs ſtomacke ſo ſtubborne, that the ſight of the rod, and threatning will not terrifie him, at length he fals to ſeuere whipping, and chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of him indeede. I pray God, that my feare and coniecture in this reſpect, may be vaine: but ſurely I feare, and by moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt ſignes am driuen to coniecture, that, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept verie ſhortly we all, euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb facs="tcp:12230:37"/> vnto the loweſt take an other courſe and trade of behauior, we muſt looke for a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full end of our long, our ſweete and pleaſant peace, that hath nowe ſo ſoundly lulled a ſleepe ſome of vs in the cradle of ſecuritie, ſome in the cradle of iniquitie, ſome in the cradle of Atheiſme, doubting of God, giuing <note place="margin">Manifeſt ſignes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme.</note> no credite to the Scriptures, diſputing of fooliſh and heathniſh queſtions, &amp; ſeeking to comprehend the works &amp; power of God, which are in the vnſcrutable wiſedome of the Lord, by reaſon and not by faith: which Saint Paule proues to be a monſtrous follie, <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> ſome in the cradle of Anabaptiſme, ſome at the breſt and ſweete teate of Poperie, all in the rolling and vnſetled cradle of our owne fantaſie. Alas, the carefull ſoules of manye thouſand poore men that haue bene oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, crie out of our land and euerye corner thereof, as the bloud of Abel for vengeance againſt our land, and againſt our hypocriſie, &amp; abuſing of our religion. What end can we imagine, what reward can we looke for, but the fearefull marke of Caine, and the heauie iudgement of the forſaken, hatefull &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Iewe? I feare greatly leaſt theſe thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and eight yeares of pleaſant peace, haue prouoked God more to anger againſt this land, then fiue hundred yeares before of warre and miſerie. O that Gods bleſsings ſhould bee ſo abuſed, that they ſhould ende
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12230:37"/> with ſo heauie a curſe. O that his mercye ſhould leade vs to ſuch vnmercifulnes, that we ſhould forget the care of our owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and fal a murdering of our owne ſoules. O that wee ſhould liue to ſee that daye, in which the ſweet benefits &amp; louing patience of the Lord ſhould make vs the worſe. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py is the man that with this Iaylor finds oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion &amp; his motions in theſe things to come vnto the Lord; and happie may that man be thought which reſteth in the Lord, which ſhall not ſee the miſerie of the future times, which ſinne and Sathan without repentance wil pul downe vpon this Noble realme, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Wee ſee farder, by the great care which this man had to know how to be ſaued, and the haſte that hee made to obtaine his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that hee gaue ſure tokens of his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his calling: which teacheth vs that the iudgements of God take not like effect in all men, For in ſome, that is, in the elect which are rightly touched by the ſpirite of God, it is true that the Prophet ſaid: <hi>Aſſone as they heare, they ſhall obey me.</hi> But in others, <note place="margin">Pſal. 18. 44.</note> this is true, <hi>I called but they would not heare nor obey.</hi> There be ſome which at the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God tremble for a time, but it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine preſently forgotten, as Pharao, the keepers of Chriſts Sepulcher, Caligula and many others. But in the godly they worke <note place="margin">Exod. 7. 3. Mat. 28. 5.</note> contrarie effects. It is true amongeſt moſt of
<pb facs="tcp:12230:38"/> vs, that the more ſignes and tokens of Gods wrath we ſee, the harder our harts grow day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: what may the ende of theſe things be? A blinde man may ſee. The Lord be merciful vnto vs, and giue vs grace with this Iaylor be more carefull of our ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>We learne alſo, that a great feſtred ſore, needeth a ſharpe and quicke Surgion. Theſe proud Rabbies and great Doctors woulde not heare the voice of the Miniſters of the Goſpell ſpeaking vnto them, neither could their voice driue them to any conſideration of their eſtate. Therfore the Lord ſent them the voice of a more terible preacher, which ſhooke both bodies and houſes all at once, aſſaying by this meanes to bring their impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent harts, to ſome ſhaking, feeling, and feare of conſcience for their ſinnes. But as <note place="margin">Which was felt about the yeare, 1580.</note> that Earthquake ſhewed them, ſo our laſt Earthquake, and other tokens ſithens, ſhew vs plainely now, the eſtate wherin we ſtand, which is, that we yet continue in our ſinnes, That we deſpiſe the voice of the Goſpel, &amp; neede a more ſharp preacher<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it openeth our ſecuritie, it threatneth Gods iuſtice in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, it promiſeth our puniſhment, &amp; ſhews vs that it is very neere the laſt time of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
                  <p>Happie (wee ſee) are they which come, when the Lord calleth them, for many bee called, but few are choſen, few come. What
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12230:38"/> callings ſhould we looke for more then wee haue had? Wee haue had our daughter diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed, our ſonne ſicke, our ſeruant like to die, wee haue ſeene fearefull ſignes ouer Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, we haue heard of the gatherings, of the confederacies and conſpiracies, of many nations againſt vs, we haue found little faith in our friends, little loyaltie in our owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall children, great falſehoode in friendly face, great diuiſions, quarrels, and hartbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings amongſt our ſelues, many <hi>Malcontent</hi> dayly riſing, and a thouſand other ſuch cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, beſides the conſideration of the ſilly threede of our happie eſtate, depending vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one, and in earthly reſpects but one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the vncertaintie of all things, when God ſhall viſite vs, the turmoyles and hurlibur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, that we may long before plainely ſee, if God of his mercy helpe not. Theſe thinges are conſidered of few, of many not accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, and feared of none. What will the ende of theſe things bee? Let all the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of England crie: <hi>Lord ſaue our Noble Queene Elizabeth from treaſon at home, and from forraine enemies abroade. Lord forgiue her her ſinnes, and vs our wickednes, and graunt, if it be thy will, that ſhe may yet long and long time in peace, and in ſaftie preſerue this her Noble Realme of England.</hi> Amen.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, we learne the great mercies of our God. For he chideth before he ſtricke, hee
<pb facs="tcp:12230:39"/> warneth before he deſtroyeth; he puniſheth not, till he haue vſed all meanes to haue vs returne. Hee giueth ſinners, both grace and ſpace to repent, and to ſeeke which waye they may be ſaued, with this ſinfull Iaylor.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="circumstance">
                  <head>The fift and last circumſtance: The time when he fell to haue this care, what hee might doe to be ſaued.</head>
                  <p>He neuer fell to this conſideration, till the Lord drew him vnto it by his ſpirit. For in the nature of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ther is no good thought motion or power to returne from euill, to conſider and ſee our ſinnes, or to lament and be ſorrie for them, and at the word to ſeeke for remedy againſt them; but rather, a deſire, will and affection ſtill to remaine in them. Therefore Chriſt ſaid. <hi>No man can come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, except my father draw him.</hi> This man <note place="margin">Iohn. 6. 37. 44. &amp; 3. 27</note> had his part of two motions. The one out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by the miracle, the other inward by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Application. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                     </label> Where firſt we ſee, that all our labour &amp; trauaile is loſt in preaching, and opening the Scripture outwardly to the eare, except the ſpirit alſo preach inwardly to the heart. For men are of themſelues deafe and dull, till God doe open their harts, and giue them a new vnderſtanding, as he gaue to Lidia, to this Iaylor and many other.</p>
                  <p>Againe we ſee, how naked, weake &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12230:39"/> we be of our ſelues: and that, if wee were not gouerned and nouriſhed by better power then our owne, how quickely &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably wee ſhould periſh. Therefore this conſideration may ſerue to conquer the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of pride in our freewill men, when they ſhall know that in their fleſh and humaine nature ther is no goodnes at all, &amp; that they can performe nothing, that is good without him that ſaid. <hi>Without me, ye can do nothing.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 7. Act. 20. 35.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What hast thou</hi> (ſaith Paule) <hi>which thou hast not receiued?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We learne that faith is not in the power &amp; nature of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to beleue or not to beleue whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <note place="margin">Ep. 1. 18. 19 1. Cor. 12 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 9 11.</note> it pleſeth him, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is the free gift of God for Chriſts ſake, vnto thoſe that are his choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For if it were in the nature of man, then all <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 29. 2. Theſ. 3, 2.</note> men ſhuld beleue. But <hi>Al men haue not faith,</hi> therefore, it is in vs a worke ſupernaturall, wrought by the ſpirite of God onely: The want of the preſence, and working of which ſpirit, in the harts of men, makes them, that they haue no deſire to heare the word, and when they doe heare it, they take no profit by it, for it is ſaide. <hi>But the word which they heard, profited them not, becauſe it was not mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 20</note> 
                     <hi>with faith in them that heard it.</hi> Where wee ſee a notable relation betweene fayth, &amp; the word. The one can neuer be effectual without the other. They goe both together. Therefore as ſoone as there was a fayth
<pb facs="tcp:12230:40"/> kindle in the hart of this Iaylor, by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, he ſeekes preſently for the word, as the body for the ſoule. For as the body is a dead thing without the ſoule, ſo the word alſo hath no life, effect or motion without faith. Now wee ſee why many Gentlemen, Countriemen and others are yet either A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſters in Religion, or deſpiſers of the word, becauſe as yet with this Iaylor they haue not receiued the gift of faith, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Here we vnderſtand, that all ſhall not be ſaued, againſt the error of Origen: for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith none can be ſaued: but none haue faith but they onely whome God the father gaue vnto his ſonne Chriſt. But hee ſaith, <hi>I pray not for the world, but for them which thou</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 17. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>haſt giuen me.</hi> Therefore the elect which are ſeparated from the world, (that is the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,) by the free election, and donation of God, and are garded by the continuall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer of Chriſt, are they onely that ſhall bee ſaued. Of which number wee ſee now this Iaylor by his calling, and faith, to bee one. For Gods election oftentimes lyeth hid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a wicked life, till the time of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion come, which the Lord hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  <p>All are not, wee ſee, drawne to Chriſt in one manner: for there bee many which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Religion, and talke much of Chriſt, whome God the father by his ſpirite neuer
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12230:40"/> drew, but either their bellie, hope of honor, vaine glorie &amp;c. No maruaile though they belieue not rightly, and though they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue not long in a good courſe. Such are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our earneſt Ieſuites, Papiſts, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine profeſſors of the Goſpell of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, when it is ſaide, that this Iaylor was drawne to this Religion &amp; to this godly care, and in like manner all the elect, wee learne what vnwillingnes, what ſlackneſſe, &amp; what negligence wee vſe in our comming to Chriſt, and that wee of our owne nature haue no liſt, affection, or good will to come, longer then God by his ſpirite, moueth vs and compelleth vs. Therefore if Chriſt ſhould looke for vs till wee ſhould come of our ſelues, wee ſhould ſurely neuer ſee him, nor haue any part in him. Let vs therefore deſire the Lord, that as he by his holy ſpirit drew this Iaylor from the miſerable thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of ignorance, error, and iniquitie, and planted a deſire in him to ſeeke the truth, and by the ſame gaue him both comfort &amp; ſaluation: So in like manner that he will by the ſame ſpirite moue our hard hearts to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our ſinne, open our blinde eyes to ſee our imperfection, and draw our proude ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makes to humble our affections, to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the word, and kindle in vs a loue to like, and ſeeke the ſame, that wee alſo in
<pb facs="tcp:12230:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> our moſt extremities, may by Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue light, helpe, and euerlaſting comfort: which the Lord God graunt vnto vs, for his deare Sonne Ieſus Chriſts ſake, to whome with the holy Ghoſt, three perſons and one eternall God, be al honor, power, praiſe, glorie and dominion both now and euer.</p>
                  <closer>Let all praiſe and glorie be giuen to God alone.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12230:41"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
